Guide to the Tompkins County anti-slavery items,1834-1848.
Tompkins County anti-slavery items
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Tompkins County anti-slavery items, 1834-1848.
2735
Joel Charles Bernard, 1945-
.1 cubic ft.
Petitions, tax schedules, and photocopies of articles.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Petitions to Congress from inhabitants of Tompkins County concerning abolition of slavery in Washington, DC, the annexation of Texas, and other anti-slavery issues, 1836-1845; tax schedules, and photocopies of articles from the Ithaca Chronicle, Ithaca Journal, Trumansburg Advertiser, and The Flag, containing speeches, letters, essays, election results and reports of anti-slavery and Free Soil meetings.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Petitions to Congress from inhabitants of Tompkins County concerning abolition of slavery in Washington, DC, the annexation of Texas, and other anti-slavery issues, 1836-1845; tax schedules, and photocopies of articles from the Ithaca Chronicle, Ithaca Journal, Trumansburg Advertiser, and The Flag, containing speeches, letters, essays, election results and reports of anti-slavery and Free Soil meetings.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Bernard, Joel Charles, 1945-; Free Soil Party (U.S.)
Titles:
Ithaca chronicle.; Ithaca journal.; Trumansburg advertiser.; The flag.
Subjects:
Abolitionists--New York (State)--Tompkins County.; Antislavery movements--New York (State)--Tompkins County.
Form and Genre Terms:
Petitions.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- Petition to Congress from Residents of Tompkins County, Nov. 1, 1838. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Petitioners request:
  1. Texas not be admitted into the Union
  2. Congress use its powers to end slavery
  3. Right of petitioning not be enjoyed
  4. No state be admitted into Union that allows slavery
- Petition to Congress from Residents of Tompkins County. Undated. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  1. No state be admitted into the Union that allows domestic slavery
  2. Rejection of all proposals for annexation of Texas
- Petition to Congress from Residents of Tompkins County. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  1. Abolition of slavery and slave trade in District of Columbia
  2. Abolition of slavery and slave trade in territories where they exist
  3. Regulation of commerce among the States, so as to prohibit domestic slave trade
- Petition to Congress from Residents of Tompkins County, Nov. 1837. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  1. Abolition of slavery in District of Columbia
  2. Abolition of internal slave trade between the States
- Petition to Congress from Residents of Tompkins County, Sept. 1, 1835, Jan. 12, 1836, and undated. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Outlawing of slavery and slave trade in District of Columbia
- Petition to Congress from Residents of Tompkins County. Undated. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Abolition of Slavery and slave trade in territory of Florida
- Petition to Congress from Residents of Tompkins County. Undated. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Regulation of commerce among states, so as to prohibit domestic slave trade
- Petition to Congress from Residents of Tompkins County. Undated. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Nonadmittance to any new state to the Union whose constitution allows domestic slavery
- Petition to Congress from Residents of Tompkins County. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  Petition request:
  Recognition of Haiti as independent
  Establishment of diplomatic and commercial relations on same footing as favored nations
- Petitions (5) to Congress from Residents of Tompkins County. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  Petition marked in red "1a" - undated
  Petition marked in red "1b" - undated
  Petition marked in red "2a" - undated
  Petition marked in red "9a" - undated
  Petition marked in red "9c" - undated
  Petitions request rejection of any propositions to annex Texas
- Page from Trumansburg Advertiser newspaper ( Aug. 28, 1839 ). Content: Announcement of Whig meeting. (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Page from Trumansburg Advertiser newspaper ( Dec. 4, 1839 ). Content: List of officers for Tompkins County Colonization Society. (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Page from Trumansburg Advertiser newspaper ( Apr. 8, 1940 ). Content: 2 articles. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  1. "Harrison and Reform" - Call for general meeting of Whigs
  2. Untitled - Endorsement of Harrison - Tyler presidential ticket
- Page from The Flag newspaper ( July 13, 1848 ). Content: (Box 1, Folder 14)
  1. Call for Democrats to rally
  2. Two political poems
- Letter "To the Free Soil Whigs," Oct. 25, 1849 (3 pages). Content: (Box 1, Folder 15)
  Call for party unity by party regulars. They want a unified party to combat the victories of the Loco Focoi Party
- Two town assessments: Ithaca, Nov. 20, 1841; Towns in Tompkins County, 1849 (Note: Though these two items are includedin the same folder, they may not be related to one another). (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Statistics concerning the Presbyterian Church, 1843 (2 pages). (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Tompkins County Election Returns, Nov. 30, 1836-Nov. 22, 1848. Folder contains returns for various town, county, state, and federal elections held during this period. Articles from Ithaca Daily Chronicle and Ithaca Journal. (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Articles on slavery, abolition, and colonization, Apr. 5, 1837-Apr. 18, 1838. Folder contains assorted articles on the issues surrounding slavery. Articles from Ithaca Daily Chronicle and The Ithaca Journal and Herald. (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Residents of Tompkins County call meeting to discuss fiscal problems they believe caused by politicians in Albany. Article appears in May 7, 1834 Ithaca Daily Chronicle. (Box 1, Folder 20)
- 1845 census for Tompkins County and New York State. Articles from the Ithaca Journal. (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Listing of New York State Senate districts, Dec. 1845. Article from Ithaca Journal is incomplete. (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Call for county meeting of Democrats. Article from Sept. 16, 1840 Ithaca Journal. (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Announcements of Free Soil meetings, July 26-Sept. 27, 1848. Articles from Ithaca Journal. (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Listing of 1848 Democratic nominations for federal, state, and local offices. Article from Oct. 25, 1848 Ithaca Journal. (Box 1, Folder 25)